

# Manoj Kumar

Email: manoj.shemar@gmail.com

Digital Profile Link: <a href="https://manojkumaraspnet.github.io/">https://manojkumaraspnet.github.io/</a>

Phone No.: 6283844778

## Key Skills



## **ABOUT**

An enthusiastic Designer/Developer/IT Trainer who strives to create applications as well as the professional life of my students. I am always ready to learn technologies to enhance my knowledge. Tech-savvy, versatile and self-directed Technology Teacher with 18 years of experience in the field of education. Highly adept in providing professional development integrating technology into existing curriculum and creating new lesson plans to encompass technology in all classrooms. Excellent organizational and team building skills distinguished by commended performance and proven results.

## PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

- Working as Head of Department in Information Technology since February 2003 at Lally Infosys.
- Worked as Faculty in About Us Incorporates from August 2000 till 02 February 2003.

## **EDUCATION**

 Master of Computer Applications (Lateral Entry), Computer Applications, 2008

Maharishi Dayanand University-Rohtak, HR

- Master of Science, Computer Science, 2006
   Maharishi Dayanand University-Rohtak, HR
- Master of Arts-Economics, 1999
   Doaba College (GNDU)-Jalandhar
- Bachelor of Arts-Economics, Political Science, 1997
   Doaba College (GNDU)-Jalandhar
- Diploma in System Administration-Jalandhar
   AboutUs Incorporates-Jalandhar

## Soft Skills



## TECHNICAL SKILLS

.NET	.NET 4.5/4.0/3.5/3.0, MVC 4.0/3.0, C# , ASP.NET,ASP.NET MVC, ASP.NET Core, VB.NET,
Technologies	ASP.NET Core
Development	Visual Studio 2015/2017, ADO. NET, SQL Server Management Studio, SSIS, SSRS, Crystal
Tools	Reports, Python using using Visual Studio for dJango, Flask, Core Services for python
Languages	C# , VB.NET, WCF, WPF, Bootstrap, JavaScript, Angular JS, JQuery, HTML, LINQ,
	XML,XAML, AJAX, Web API,REST API, WSDL, Python
Databases	SQL Server 2012/2016,T-SQL ,Oracle 11g, MS ACCESS 2016
Operating	Windows 7, Windows 2008, Windows 2010, Linux
Systems	
Additional Skills	J2SE, J2EE, Basic Unix, Linux Commands
Designing	Corel-Draw, Adobe Photoshop, and Adobe Illustrator

- Expertise in developing applications using Microsoft technologies such as .NET Framework
   4.0/3.5/3.0/2.0, Web applications using ASP.NET, and distributed applications using WCF, XML Web Services and Messaging system.
- Working closely to the client for requirement gathering and analysis and provided desired solution to client in time limits.
- Experience in Writing code and debugging skills with ASP.NET, WCF, C#, Web services.
- Involved in implementation of Object Oriented Concepts during the development.
- Developing the application using MVC, Entity Data Model and RESTful and WCF services.
- Responsible for UI design and creating contracts and classes in WCF for different modules in the application.
- Developed reports using MS SQL Server Reporting Services and Crystal Reports.
- Implemented UI using MVC 4.0, HTML, XML, CSS, JavaScript, AngularJS, AJAX and Web Form Controls to create responsive web pages, developed Master Pages.
- Using JQuery and JavaScript for implementing client side validations at Controller level.
- Using JQuery JSON for dynamic User Interface, retrieval and posting of data.
- Implemented .Net Security features of Authentication and Authorization using .Net Membership.
- JQuery and JavaScript for implementing client side validations at Controller level.
- Using JQuery JSON for dynamic User Interface, retrieval and posting of data.
- Implemented .Net Security features of Authentication and Authorization using .Net Membership.
- Implemented .Net classes for Business logic Layer using C# .

## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## **HEAD OF IT-DEPARTMENT, 02/2003 - TILL DATE**

Lally Infosys - Jalandhar, Punjab

- Providing technical solutions to the trainees in various technologies like C, C++, Java (J2SE-J2EE), C#
   .NET, ASP .NET MVC, Python, Web Application Development, Mobile Application using Android.
- Created new lessons plans based on course objectives.
- System and Network Management.
- Conduct teacher trainings and seminars on new technologies.
- Team management
- Handling company websites, web pages and advertising on social media.
- Handing IT Projects development.
- Designing Marketing Material using Corel-Draw, Adobe Photoshop, and Adobe Illustrator.

#### FACULTY MEMBER, 08/2002 TO 02/2003

AboutUs Incorporates – Jalandhar, Punjab

- Taught Students C, C++, VB6.0, Oracle 9i, 10, Web Technologies like HTML, CSS, FrontPage, JavaScript, and ASP.
- Created new lessons plans based on course objectives.
- Project Management

#### PART TIME COMPUTER INSTRUCTOR, 05/2002 TO 02/2003

Mavav Sehyog Society - Jalandhar, Punjab

- Verified data integrity and accuracy
- Teaching Web Designing and Web Development
- Given Training to faculties on Oracle SQL-PLSQL Commands

#### **COLLABORATION WITH OTHER ORGANISATIONS**

- **Doardarshan Kender Jalandhar Govt. Of India** Invites me time to time for their Program on Technical Education)
- AIR (All India Radio) Govt. Of India Jalandhar invited me on Social Media Pros-Cons.
- Given Career Guidance Seminars in different Schools and Colleges.
- Given Seminar on .NET Technologies to Technical Faculties of PTUDEP Program Govt. Of Punjab .
- Taking Online Classes of Overseas Students.
- Participating in Social Activities for the betterment of the Society. (Tree Plantation, Signature
  Campaign like Anti-Terrorism Campaign, Anti Drug Campaign, Smart City Jalandhar Campaign, Female
  Foeticide Campaign, World Women Day Campaign, Punjabi Jan-Jagriti Rally to promote Punjabi Maa
  Boli, Traffic Rules Awareness Rally)
- Regular Blood Donor from last 10 years donating blood after every 6 Months, honored by Pehal an NGO on World Donor Day at DAV College for donating blood regularly.
- Taking Seminar on Responsive Website Development to Engg. Students from different Colleges and universities at Lally Infosys and also their campus (DAVIET-DAV Engineering College, DIPS College, Dr.B.R Ambedkar National Institute of Technology, GNDU Regional Campus of Engineering, GNDU regional Campus Jalandhar).
- Participating in ZEE TV Campaign "Decision For vote Without Religion "

- Coding and Tuning the queries, Stored procedures and functions, Triggers using PL/SQL
- Implemented Data Access Layer using Entity Framework to connect, retrieve and update the data from SQL server.
- Developed Windows Development with VB.NET.
- Creating Queries and joins on multiple tables, Functions and Triggers using LINQ in SQL 2012 for inserting/updating/ deleting the data into the relational tables.
- Developing various Stored Procedures for the data retrieval from the database and generating different types of reports.
- Involve in object oriented analysis and design using UML Unified Modeling Language such as use case, activity, sequence, class and component diagrams using Visio.
- Interface with database and stored procedure using ADO.NET Dataset, Data Reader, Data Adapter, Data Grid, Grid View.
- Wrote Queries and Stored Procedures for integrating database for CRUD operations with databases.
- Worked on creating tables, views, triggers, sequences, constraints, Stored Procedures, Functions, and Packages using SQL, and PL/SQL based on the documented user requirements.
- Responsible for redeveloping and configuring AngularJS for better responsive UI
- JQuery and JavaScript is also used for client side validations.
- Troubleshoot and provided resolution for different kind of issues during the various stages of project.
- Used Java Script to validate the user input.
- Fixing various bugs as well as enhancing quality with performance for both applications.
- Designed database in MS SQL Server by creating Tables, Stored Procedures, Functions, Views and Triggers and integrate them in the applications.
- Created classes using VB.NET and develop database components to access database using ADO.NET

#### Recommendation Letter from Microsoft Certified Student :-



Gaurav Bhardwai

Technical Consultant at Deloitte USI

Presently working on Machine Learning and Deep Learning.

developergaurav@outlook.com

+91-9803462179

Hi, I am really fortunate enough to take training from Manoj Sir in Microsoft .NET. Under his guidance, I achieved 10+ Microsoft Technical Certifications. He teaches students in a very practical way which is very beneficial for them amd make them industry ready. I took training in Microsoft .NET in which he helped me in various real world assignments which leveraged my career beyond the limits

## PROJECTS UNDERTAKEN

- Web Application for **Blood Bank** using **spring in J2EE**.
- Website of lally Infosys http://www.lallyinfosys.com
- Website of the jatt Sikh council (NGO) http://www. http://thejatsikhcouncil.com
- Website of Taste of Punjab Canada http://www.http://tasteofpunjabltd.ca
- Website of Fikre-Hondh (NGO) http://www.http://fikrehondh.com
- Mobile Application for Beggar Finger Data Scan (Android) for Beggar Free Smart City

## **CERTIFICATES**

- Got First Runner Up in Once Act Play In National Youth Festival Held at Chennai in 1998
- Got Second Position Certificate from GNDU in One Act Play in 1997.
- Certified Regular Blood Donor by Pehal NGO and SBTC Punjab from 2008.
- Got First Position Certificate by Rotary Club Of Jullundhur for Mono Acting in 1997
- Got Certificate for Typing from GEE DEE Commercial College Jalandhar In 1994.

## **ACHIEVMENTS**

Students trained under my guidance are placed in Government as well as private sectors. They are working as professionals in MNCs like Dell, Wipro, HCL, TCS, Cognate, Infosys, Accenture, KPMG etc. Below are the students mentioned who are working in MNCS:-

- Gaurav Bhardhwaj Technical Consultant , Deloitte USI (developergaurav@outlook.com)
- Ravneet Puri Systems Ananlyst, States of California (ravneetpuri7@gmail.com)
- Lovepreet Singh Software Developer, Deloitte (lovepreetsingh.3097@gmail.com)
- Simrandeep kaur Analyst in Canadian Food Inspection Agency, Government of Canada (simrandeepkaur090998@gmail.com)
- Vipanjeet Singh Application Ananlyst Northern Health, Britich Columbia, Canada (vipanjeet.singh@northernhealth.ca)
- Ripu Raman Senior Govt. Computer Teacher, Govt. Sr. Sec. Sofi Village, Jalandhar Cantt. (ripuraman@yahoo.com)
- Avneet Kaur Narula Senior Govt. Computer Teacher, Nehru Garden Govt. Sr. Sec. School, Jalandhar. (coolavi\_nancy@yahoo.com)

## **HOBBIES**

- Work Out in Gym.
- Yoga, Walking
- Reading IT magazines.